<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise against the priesthood &amp; sacrifice of the Church of Rome wherein the simple may perceiue their intollerable impietie, usurping that office and action, which euer appertaine to Christ onely / by G.G.</title>
            <author>G. G.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11493.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24493621</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24493621</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise against the priesthood &amp; sacrifice of the Church of Rome wherein the simple may perceiue their intollerable impietie, usurping that office and action, which euer appertaine to Christ onely / by G.G.</title>
                  <author>G. G.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Midleton for Tobie Cooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹ B-D⁸ E⁶.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27731:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27731:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE TREATISE againſt the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood &amp; Sacrifice of the Church of Rome:</p>
            <p>Wherein the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may perceiue their intollerable impietie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping that office and action, which euer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to Chriſt onely, by G. G.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by H. Midleton for <hi>Tobie Cooke,</hi> 1584.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:27731:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27731:2"/>
            <head>A BREEFE Treatiſe againſt the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Sacrifice of the Church of Rome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Pope &amp; his cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie do ſtiffely affirme and go about to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that they bée Prieſts, and that it is an holie Prieſthoode which they haue: euen the Prieſthood of the Newe Teſtament. Further al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they boaſt, that the ſacrifice which they offer, is the ſonne of God himſelf, euen Chriſt Ieſus, God and man, fleſh, bloud, and bone, as he was borne of the bleſſed virgin. We on the contrarie affirme that they be verie <hi>Baalamites,</hi> and not Prieſts of the Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and that their ſacrifice is not the ſonne of God, but the ſtinking and Idolatrous ſacrifice of Antichriſt. Who ſhalbe beléeued? we or they? Let neither of both for our ſelues haue any credit at all. For what is man, that he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27731:3"/> ſhould haue any credit? Let neither of vs be our owne Judge, for then there would be partialitie: But let God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrike the ſtroke, let him alone pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence, let that part he credited which hath his witneſſe &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie. When he ſpeaketh, let man kéepe ſilence: When he pronounceth ſentence, let the mouth of all fleſh be ſhut vp: For who ſhall reply againſt the wordes of his mouth, which are in perfect trueth and wiſedome? His te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie hath he expreſſely ſet downe in the ſacred Scriptures, his voyce hath he there vttered, to declare his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect minde and will: Let them be brought foorth, and heard, ſearch them, for ſo are ye willed. Craue the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding at his hands, who is the onely teacher. If by them it be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proued vnto you, that the popiſh Prieſts be not the Prieſts of the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we Teſtament, nor their ſacrifice the ſonne of God, then let men no longer doubt, but that all their whole worſhip is idolatrous and Antichriſtian. For it their prieſthood and ſacrifice, which are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27731:3"/> the two principal things be aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, what can be good in them? Let vs come to the triall of the matter. And firſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (which they deny not) the worde doth teach, that the dignitic, priuilege, and office of the holic Prieſt, is to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch into the preſence of God, to offer giftes, and ſacrifice, and to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and ſupplication for the people. The neceſſitie of this office doth come from the profaneſſe and impuritie of men. All men are vncleane ſinners, God is moſt pure &amp; holie, and doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly hate ſinne: And for the ſame cauſe he doth curſſe and reiect all thoſe which are polluted therwith. They can not approche, nor indure his preſence, before whome nothing vncleane can ſtand. The prayers which come from them cannot be heard, being the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſinners, and therefore not clean. No gift can be accepted at their hands, to make any reconcilement, or to get any fauour, they and all theirs are ſtill reiected, they muſt either haue ſome other to do it for them, or elſe for euer remaine ſtill out of fauour, and be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27731:4"/> caſt away in eternall perdition. He that ſhall do it, muſt be without ſpot of ſinne, and therefore among all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> onely Jeſus Chriſt is found worthie &amp; able to execute this office. For if we reſpect this great worke of reconciliation betweene God and men, we ſhall finde that alone he hath wrought it, and therefore is the onely Prieſt of God. None other can in ſuch conſideration be called Prieſtes. It is true in deede that <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated &amp; made prieſts, and did execute the miniſterie of the prieſthood in the Temple: But yet as their ſacrifices did not, nor could not take away ſinne, being but ſhadowes and the reſemblance of the ſacrifice of Chriſt, ſo alſo they were not ſacrifices in déede, but ſo called, for that they were the patterne of that which is the true ſacrifice. The ſame is to be ſaide of the Prieſtes, that they were no otherwiſe Prieſtes, but in figure, becauſe they did reſemble Chriſt, who alone is a Prieſt in trueth. Thoſe other Prieſtes were ſeparated from the people, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27731:4"/> to the ſeruice of the Temple. The chiefe of them might enter into the moſt holie place, and come before the Arke of the couenant and the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſeate, and there offer with bloud to make reconciliation. They bare the names of the tribes of Iſrael, and ſo preſented them before the Lorde. But yet all was but a ſhadow, to direct the eyes of their faith vnto Chriſt: for theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prieſtes could not waſh away ſinne, they could not bring men into heauen, and therefore when he came, which is the Prieſt in deede, and which doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh that which was by them but reſembled: then all thoſe ſhadowes did ceaſe and giue place. He continueth a Prieſt for euer. He hath perfectly wrought the worke of reconciliation, &amp; brought me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into fauour with God. For with the ſacrifice of his bodie he hath ranſomed them, and with his bloud he hath purged away their ſinnes with full ſatiſfaction, and his prayers haue béene accepted. He hath receiued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; power to ſaue for euer all thoſe whome he doth ſanctifie. Now the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27731:5"/> is, whether any can be ioyned with him in this office, and be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with him in this high dignitie, as to offer vp to God the ſame ſacrifice which he offered. For this is without all controuerſie, that ſuch as do chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a copartnerſhip with him in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring the ſacrifice, and gift which he did offer, do alſo challenge a fellowſhip with him in the dignitie and glorie of the Prieſthood by which he did offer it. For was not the great glorie of his Prieſthood in this, that he offred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſacrifice vnto his father? ſhall not thoſe then which do the ſame thing receiue the ſame honour &amp; glorie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Thus we ſée that when as none could be found worthie in heauen and earth, but onely the Lambe, <hi>Reuela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 5. yet euerie greaſie ſhaueling will haue fellowſhip and glorie with him, euen in the higheſt part of his office. Lord how long wilt thou ſpare? looke downe and viſite the blaſphemie of the wicked beaſt, vpon him, and vpon the head &amp; route of his horned ſhauelings. They ſay they be Prieſtes, doubtles then are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27731:5"/> they mediators of the Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For the Teſtament &amp; the Prieſt are ioyned together, the Prieſt of the Newe Teſtament is the mediatour of the Newe Teſtament. For Chriſt is compared with <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, to haue obtained a miniſterie ſo much more excellent, as he is the mediatour of a better Teſtament. <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> 8. 6. The excellencie of the miniſterie of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, was according to the worthineſſe of the Teſtament, wherof they were the mediators. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, they could not haue that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be Prieſtes, or mediators of that Teſtament, wherein there was but the ſhadow of good things to come, <hi>Hebrew.</hi> 10. 1. vnleſſe it had béene giuen them of God: as it is expreſſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. where he ſpeaketh of that Prieſthood of the lawe, which hath now ceaſed. Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none could haue this honour to be a Prieſt of the olde Teſtament, but ſuch as were called of God as was <hi>Aaron:</hi> then how much leſſe ſhall any be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this dignitie with the ſonne of God, to be the Prieſtes &amp; mediators
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27731:6"/> of the newe couenant, but ſuch as can ſhewe that God hath giuen them this honour? Chriſt did not take this honor to him ſelfe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. but he that ſaid. Thou art my ſonne, this day haue I begotten thée, gaue it him. The Lords ſware that he ſhould be a prieſt. Let the Papiſts ſhewe any calling which they haue of God vnto this glorie of the Prieſthood: Let them ſhewe any one place out of the new Teſtament, where Chriſt did ordeine Prieſtes: Finally, let them ſhewe where euer <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or any Apoſtle or miniſter of the Goſpel, haue called themſelues prieſts, or haue béen ſo called by others, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than that which they giue vnto all the faithfull, that being waſhed &amp; ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in the bloud of Chriſt, they be made Kings and Prieſtes vnto God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pet. 2. Reuel. 1. &amp;</hi> 5. which is in another ſenſe than this which they challenge. No, the worde of the Lorde is directly againſt you, ye prieſts of <hi>Baal.</hi> For it ſpeaketh of one Prieſt which ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> &amp; not of prieſts. It ſayeth, there is one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27731:6"/> mediatour betwéene God and man, 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2. And therefore alſo it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that there is but one Prieſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Prieſt of the new Teſtament is the mediator of the ſame, is there any man ſo mad as to aſcribe this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Pope and his prieſtes, as to ſay they be mediators of the newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? If not, then are they no prieſts. Nowe, although this is ſufficient to prooue their prieſthood to be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait, that they can ſhewe no calling in the worde, nor no mention that any one of the Apoſtles was a prieſt, or that any man ſhould haue ſuch honour: yet to make the matter more euident, I will ſhewe by further reaſons, that their prieſthood is ſuch, that it cannot ſtand with the prieſthood of Chriſt. We al knowe, that the Lord ſwore that his ſonne ſhould ariſe vp a Prieſt for euer, after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech, Pſa.</hi> 110 Then if it fall out, as it ſhalbe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhewed, that the Prieſthood of the Papacie is directly contrary vnto that order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> It muſt néedes alſo followe that the ſame is not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27731:7"/> of God. The order of the prieſthood of <hi>Mechiſedech</hi> is gathered out of that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Geneſis.</hi> 14. the wordes are theſe: And <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> King of <hi>Salem</hi> brought foorth bread &amp; wine, which was alſo a prieſt of the moſt high God. And he bleſſed him, ſaying, Bleſſed be <hi>Abram</hi> of the moſt high God, poſſeſſor of heauen and earth, and bleſſed be the moſt high God, which hath deliuered thine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries into thine hand, and he gaue him tythe of all. This man was greater than the Patriarche <hi>Abraham,</hi> as it is proued by two reaſons, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. the one that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid him tithes: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he bleſſed <hi>Abraham.</hi> Then <hi>Moſes</hi> writing of ſo great a man, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mentioning father nor mother, nor kindred, beginning, nor end of his life: although he had a father and a mother, and kinred, and had both a beginning and an end: yet becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth not any of theſe, it is ſaid, that he was without father, without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without kinred, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of dayes, and without ende of life,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27731:7"/> as though he were one that had ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come downe from heauen. When it is ſaide, that he was a Prieſt of the moſt high God, no mention made of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny annoynting, of any miniſtring gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of any temple, altar, or ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nor yet of any that did ſuccéede him, it is gathered that he doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a prieſt for euer. And moreouer, that in his Prieſthood all thinges are ſpirituall and full of endles power. By this argument, the holy Ghoſt proueth <hi>Hebr. 7. ver.</hi> 16. 17. 18. that the prieſthood of the Leuites was abrogate, and could not ſtand with the Prieſthood of Chriſt, ſéeing it could giue no ſtrength nor fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance thereto: for the one being ſpirituall, and according to the power of the life that is not diſſolued, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as he ſpeaketh being after the law of the carnall commaundement. they could not be ioyned ſo together as that the one might be a ſupply vnto the defect of the other. For although the law of the carnall commaundement, which is ſo called, not in reſpect of the founder thereof, which was God, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27731:8"/> for that the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the things were bodily and carnall) did profit and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite men thus farre, that by outwarde carnall things, they had the reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance of things ſpirituall to ſtrengthen their faith. Yet when he was come, in whom was all the ſpirituall and heauenly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Prieſthood, thoſe carnal and earthly things were to ceaſe. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: <hi>Aaron</hi> was annointed with ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teriall oyle, he was clothed with the miniſtring garments, he entred into a tabernacle vpon earth which was built with hands, he had the bloud of calues and goates, and ſlaine beaſtes for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, hee preſented the names of the tribes before the mercie ſeat. All theſe and ſuch like are the carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe did not take away ſinne, nor reſtore into fauour with God: But Chriſt alone is the Prieſt that wrought that. His annoynting was not with oyle, but with the holie Ghoſt: He nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no holie garments, for there was no ſpot of vncleannes in him to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. He came not with the bloud of ſlaine beaſtes, but with his own bloud.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27731:8"/> He entred not into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Tabernacle made with hands, to appeare for vs, and to preſent vs before the Arke: but he is entred into the very heauens, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the throne of God, to preſent vs there. Thus then it followeth that the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> being after the law of the carnall commaundement, that is to ſaye, the conſecration was with things that were earthly and of a bodily ſubſtance, the ſacrifices alſo of the ſame ſort, it could do nothing. But the Prieſthood of Chriſt, wherein all things are heauenly and ſpirituall, and full of endleſſe power, hath fully and perfectly accompliſhed the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. If this order then of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> wherin there is nothing carnall, did aboliſh the order of the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> wherein al things were carnall, becauſe the carnall things cannot helpe at al to bring men to heauen, and becauſe the order of the one Prieſthood did ſo differ from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as being of a quite contrarie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: It muſt néedes followe that the Prieſthood of the Papacie cannot ſtand
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27731:9"/> with the Prieſthood of Chriſt, becauſe it is alſo carnall. For was the oyle vpon <hi>Aaron</hi> carnall, and is not their annoynting &amp; ſhauing carnall? Were all the miniſtring garments of <hi>Aaron</hi> carnall, and are not their veſtments, as the Cope, the Surpleſſe, the Amiſſe, and other ſuch holie and prieſtly robes carnall? Was the Altar in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple carnall, and all the miniſtring veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that did belong thereto, and are not the Altars of theſe carnall? Were <hi>Aarons</hi> incenſe and oblations carnall: and are not the oblations of theſe, and all their incenſe, and other things car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? Thoſe former could not ſtande with the Prieſthood of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe they were in ſubſtance carnall: howe then ſhall theſe latter, which are as carnall as they? Tell vs, O ye <hi>Baalamites</hi> of the Romiſh order, wherefore your order ſhould in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be called the order of <hi>Melchiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech,</hi> ſeeing it is as contrarie vnto it as was that of <hi>Aaron?</hi> The order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> is gathered out of the deſcription of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be without any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27731:9"/> annoynting with oyle, without gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the miniſtration, without Tabernacle, without Altar, without ſacrifice, without any earthly thing. And why? becauſe his order is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and therefore all things thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing muſt be ſpirituall: it is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and full of endles power, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing which appertaineth to the execution there of muſt be tranſitorie &amp; weake. For ſhall an earthly temple, an Altar of ſtone, garments of ſilke, or of any corruptible thing be fit to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with that prieſthood which is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting? There is no doubt, but that euery thing for the execution of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, muſt be agreeable vnto the nature of the Prieſthood it ſelfe: and therefore as there is nothing mentioned in <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> that is carnall, ſo alſo we ſée that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, a Prieſt after that order hath executed that function without any ſuch thinges conſecrated thereunto. How ſhall the Papiſtes then which haue their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood executed altogether in ſuch things as be tranſitorie, challenge to be of that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27731:10"/> order with our ſauiour, wherein as the Prieſthood is heauenly and eternall, ſo are all things there to belonging. But peraduenture ye will ſay: <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> was a Prieſt, and he offred ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices to God as other Prieſts at that time. Wherefore ſhould it then be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that there was no carnall thing in ſubſtance belonging to the execution of his function? He had an Altar, he had beaſtes to offer, and no doubt did offer. I aunſwere that albeit <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech</hi> did execute the Prieſtes office, after the manner of other Prieſts, yet that is nothing to the purpoſe. For the order of his Prieſthood is gathered out of that deſcription of <hi>Moſes</hi> in which there is no mention of ſuch things. We are not to doubt but that he had father and mother, that he was borne as an other man, and alſo had an ende of his dayes: Neuertheleſſe, becauſe thoſe things are left out, he is brought in as one which neuer had beginning, &amp; that neuer had ende, but continueth a prieſt for euer. In like ſort, howſoeuer at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time he executed the office of a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27731:10"/> prieſt, as others did: yet becauſe there is no ſuch thing expreſſed, &amp; that which is expreſſed, is that wherein he is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the ſonne of God, it is ſaide, that he was a prieſt after another or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that there was nothing carnal in his prieſthood. Therefore we are to conclude, that the prieſthood of the new teſtament hauing nothing in it that is carnall, the prieſthood of the Papacie being &amp; conſiſting altogether of things carnall, and ſuch as were alſo the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of men, it muſt néedes followe that they are not prieſtes of any teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, but the prieſtes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Further, let it be conſidered, that a Prieſt muſt ariſe after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> that ſhall ſo continue for euer: For the eternall ſonne of God was reſembled by <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> in that he is brought in without any beginning: The continuance alſo of his office for euer, in that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaide of his death nor of any that did ſuccéede him. This then being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, what impudent wretches are thoſe which being mortall men, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27731:11"/> haue an ende, dare ſo blaſphemouſly boaſt, that they be Prieſts after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Melchiſedech?</hi> how ſhall they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to anſwere vnto this? The Prieſt of the New Teſtament is after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> that is to ſay, a Prieſt for euer, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without end, without any to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede him? Their prieſthood hath a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, it hath an ende, they haue thoſe that do ſuccéed one after another. If this be a materiall point in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Prieſthood which Chriſt ſhoulde be after, as none vnleſſe his forehead be of braſſe dare denie, that it ſhould be for euer: What a childiſhnes were it for any man to thinke that the prieſthood of the Papacie is the ſame when it doth faile in that which is eſſentiall? For they die and come to an ende. Are not theſe contrarie the one to the other, to continue a Prieſt for euer as <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> in figure, and Chriſt in déede, and to be Prieſtes for certaine yeares, and then to ceaſe by reaſon of death? Are not then the Prieſtes made at <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> contrary to this order, yea, as contrary
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27731:11"/> as light is vnto darknes, or as heauen is vnto hell? And muſt it not ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that ſéeing they be no Prieſtes of the olde Teſtament, nor can not be Prieſtes of the New, vnto the which their order is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, that their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may be as good as the prieſthood of <hi>Baal,</hi> and better it cannot be? For if it be not of God, is it not then of the diuel? Let all true Chriſtians therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with deteſtation this helliſh ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the Romiſh biſhop, who being a prieſt after the diuels order, yet ſayeth he is after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi> Moreouer it is to be noted, which the holy Ghoſt ſayeth <hi>Hebr. 7. ver.</hi> 26. that ſuch an high Prieſt it became vs to haue, as was holie, harmeleſſe, vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſeparate from ſinners, and made higher than the heauens. This ſetteth foorth the puritie, and alſo the high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which of neceſſitie are required in that Prieſt, that ſhal deale in our cauſe to bring vs to God. For if he were a ſinner himſelf, how ſhould he come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God? If he were ſpotted with any vncleannes, how ſhould he purchaſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27731:12"/> for others? ſeeing he ſhould him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be out of fauour. If he were vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, how ſhould he ſanctifie and make ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thoſe whome he doeth preſent vnto God? In like ſort it is to be weighed, how great that man muſt be of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is to enter eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the throne of glorie, and there abide, as one able to ſaue all that come vnto God by him. For thus he muſt be made higher than the heauens, and aboue all creatures in the heauens. For albeit the holy and bleſſed Angels be ſeparate from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and be alſo about the throne of God, yet no one of them hath this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be made higher than the heauens, none of them then can haue the honour of the Prieſthood, to obtaine pardon of ſinnes for the Church, that glorie and power being reſerued only to the ſonne who is farre aboue principalities and powers. Such a Prieſt as this muſt bring vs that are baſe and ſinful wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnto God, in him we muſt be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, in him we muſt obtaine fauour, in him we muſt be heard, that is ſo high in fauour, that no requeſt can be denied
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27731:12"/> him. In him wee muſt be ſaued who hath receiued all power and authoritie both in heauen and earth, and liueth for euer. What fouler beaſtlines then can there be than this, that ſinfull, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, and baſe wormes of the earth, ſhoulde challenge vnto themſelues to be Prieſtes of the Newe Teſtament? yea, that ſuch ſillie Aſſes, as are ſcarce fit to kéepe ſwine, will yet haue that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that the glorie, honor, and power of, is aboue the Angels, let all men iudge nowe of this concluſion. The Prieſt of the New Teſtament is pure and holie, ſeparated from ſinners, made higher than the heauens. The Pope &amp; all his broode are ſinfull whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, théeues and murtherers, baſe and vile wretches of the earth, farre off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being higher than the heauens. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their prieſthood is not the prieſthood of the Newe Teſtament. There is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo another notable difference betwéene the olde prieſthood and the newe: that thoſe former did miniſter in earth, in a Tabernacle made with handes, which had no enduring ſubſtance: This latter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27731:13"/> is entred into the Sanctuarie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and there doth execute the Prieſts office, hee doeth not any thing in an earthly ſanctuarie. For why this prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is heauenly and eternall, his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle muſt be agreeable vnto the ſame. And it is ſaide that if he were on earth, he could not be a Prieſt, while thoſe Prieſtes did ſtande which were after the law, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8. 4. For although our Lord were a Prieſt in deede when he was vpon earth, and did offer the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his body, yet ye ſee there was no outward thing that the Prieſts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth do. His bodie was ſlaine vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth, but was it carried into the Temple, and ſlaine at the Altar? Was the bloud ſprinkled before the Arke of the couenant? No, all things were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and ſpirituall in this ſacrifice. If we regard the ſubſtance of his bodie, it was the ſame that ours is. But yet all the vertue &amp; efficacie of the ſame, when it was a ſlaine ſacrifice, was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue. And ſo though he were in earth, yet the whole fruite of his worke was in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For he being both God and man,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27731:13"/> was a Prieſt euen then in heauen, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſlaine vpon earth. The vertue and power of the ſacrifice to purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſinne, was not of the manhood, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe: but the manhood had it from the Godhead, in that the manhood was ſo vnited vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godhead, that they made one perſon. In this ſenſe he ſayth, <hi>Iohn 6. ver.</hi> 63. It is the ſpirite that quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the fleſh profiteth nothing. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the fleſh of Chriſt hath power in it forgiue life, as in déede it is the bread of life, and whoſoeuer doeth eate of it ſhall liue for euer: yet it hath not this life of it ſelfe, but from the Godhead: Likewiſe the bloud is able to purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſinne, becauſe it is the bloud of a man which is alſo God. It is alſo ſaid, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. The firſt man was of the earth earthly. The ſeconde man was the Lord fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen heauenly. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he called a man from heauen heauenly? was it becauſe his fleſh was from heauen? curſed be he which ſo hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. No, it was becauſe all the vertue and efficacie which was in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to redéeme the worlde, was from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27731:14"/> heauen. We ſée then that he being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed in earth, the efficacie of his Prieſthood was in heauen. There is nothing in his Prieſthood, nor in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof which is earthly. But theſe prieſtes are altogether earth, and what can they do without earthe A tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they muſt haue on earth, an Altar of earth, manie other things of earth, which prooue that all their miniſterie &amp; function is earthie. Then to conclude, the mediatour of the New Teſtament is not a Prieſt vpon earth, nor execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the Prieſtes office but in the heauenly Tabernacle. The <hi>Romanes</hi> are Prieſts vpon earth, they miniſter with earthly things in earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, and vpon Altares concecrate to that purpoſe. Who doth not ſée there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they haue no affinitie at all with Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if it may be demaunded, is <hi>ſir Iohn</hi> a King: Surely then haue there béene manie louſie Kings. Euery one which is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> is a King, for thoſe two are ioyned together in his order, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27731:14"/> kingdome, and the Prieſthood. Is there any man ſo fooliſh as to take theſe to be kings? They may be taken for prieſts, but not after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> ſo long as they haue but ſhauen crownes, and not crownes of golde, nor after the order of <hi>Aaron</hi> which is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but after the order of the prieſts of <hi>Baal.</hi> If they obiect that the Pope hath both ſwordes, the ſpirituall, and the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, and therefore he is a King and a Prieſt, I aunſwere, that therein he is more vnlike Chriſt, whoſe kingdome is not of this world. The kingdome of Chriſt is ſpirituall, he medled not with the ciuil ſworde, but left it to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: The Pope chalenging it, is not of that order which Chriſt is. Seing then, as we haue prooued, none can be partakers with Chriſt in the moſt high dignitie and honour of the Prieſthoode, ſeeing euerie Prieſt is a mediatour of a Teſtament, and of the Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is but one, ſeeing none can haue that honour to be Prieſt, but they which are called of God, and the Papiſtes can ſhewe no calling, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27731:15"/> of Prieſtes in the Newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Seeing in the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech,</hi> all things are ſpirituall and full of endleſſe power, in the order of Poperie all things carnall, <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> continueth for euer, theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Séeing alſo the Prieſt of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament muſt be perfectly holie &amp; pure, without ſpot of ſinne, and higher than the heauens, the Popiſh Prieſtes are abominable ſinners: Chriſt is a Prieſt in heauen, they vpon earth: He is both a King and a Prieſt, <hi>ſir Iohn</hi> is not a king: It doth followe, that their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Prieſthood is not of God: but they be the idolatrous prieſtes of Antichriſt. They can not by their miniſterie and Prieſthood bring men vnto God, but contrariwiſe they carrie headlong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diuel. Such therefore as will ſaue their ſoules muſt not be blind and wilfull, but open their eyes and behold the cléere and manifeſt trueth of God, which he hath taught in his worde. As we haue proued this one part, ſo let vs now come to the other, that is, to ſhew that the ſacrifice which they offer, is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27731:15"/> not the ſonne of God, but a wicked ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination, no more pleaſing vnto God, than if men ſhould offer a dogge in ſacrifice vnto him. It might ſuffice to ſatiſfie a modeſt minde, that al which they doe is naught, becauſe they doe make themſelues Prieſts after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> and ſo do challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to themſelues greater honour than any Angel hath, euen the honour that is due alone vnto the onely begotten ſonne of God. And yet where the ſcripture ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that this honour was giuen vnto Chriſt with an oth, they will haue part with him, being not able to bring one ſentence of the worde to prooue that there ſhoulde be any Prieſt beſides Chriſt. He neuer ordained any Prieſt, no one of his Apoſtles was called a Prieſt, and in euerie point their order is ſo contrarie vnto the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech,</hi> this I ſay might ſatiſfie: but yet to lay open their trecherie further, we will proue that they haue abuſed the world, and made them worſhip that for God which was but a cake of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. I will not goe farre for proofe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27731:16"/> hereof: for it is manifeſtly and fully to be prooued by that which the holie Ghoſt hath ſet downe as concerning the ſacrifice of the Newe Teſtament in the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> Thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are there brought to proue that the ſacrifices of the lawe could doe nothing, and therefore were to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, will alſo ſerue to throw downe the abominable idol of the Papiſts. For if the weaknes of thoſe former ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were gathered by their nature and order which was vſed in them, then ſhall the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, if it bee founde to differ as farre and further from that of Chriſtes, than thoſe, be found not to be the ſacrifice of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Chap. 9. ver.</hi> 1. it is ſaide, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer couenant had alſo ordinances of religion, and a worldly ſanctuarie, and there he doth repeat particularly ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie things, as the candleſtick, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the ſhew bread, the golden cenſure, the Arke of the Teſtament, the golden pot with Manna, <hi>Aarons</hi> rod that had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27731:16"/> budded, and the tables of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In this worldly Sanctuarie, with theſe foreſaide ordinances of the ſame nature, did the prieſtes of the law exerciſe their office: and this is one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prooue that their Prieſthood was weake and coulde not bring men vnto God. For the habitation of God is in the heauens, there is his throne of glorie, and moſt high maieſtie: thither muſt thoſe be brought which ſhal come vnto him: whereupon it followeth that the Prieſt that ſhall bring men vnto God, muſt be a miniſter of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of Heauen. For the entring into the holie place made with handes, &amp; the miniſtring in the ſame with ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the like nature, that is to ſaye earthly a tranſitorie, can by no meanes bring men eternally vnto God: For how ſhall earthly things compaſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, or things which vaniſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, bring that to paſſe which ſhall laſt for euer? Thoſe Prieſtes therefore, whoſe prieſthood was tranſitorie, for their prieſthood muſt needes be of the ſame nature and condition that their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27731:17"/> temple and ordinances were, and can ſtand no longer than they, were for to ceaſe, when the time was come vnto which they were prefixed. Vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe is Chriſt oppoſed in the ſame <hi>Chapter, ver. 24.</hi> where he ſayeth that Chriſt is not entred into the holie places made with handes, which are ſimilitudes of the true ſanctuarie, but is entred into heauen it ſelfe to appeare in the ſight of God for vs. For as the ſacrifice which he offred was heauenly and of eternall power, ſo alſo is his Tabernacle, and likewiſe his Prieſthood. For thoſe three muſt euer be ioyned together. Then if the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices could do nothing, but were to ceaſe becauſe their Tabernacle and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were worldly: how much leſſe ſhall the greaſie Popiſh prieſtes be able to offer any ſacrifice to appeaſe Gods wrath, ſéeing the ſacrifice which muſt do that, is heauenly and ſpiritual, and cannot be offred in a worldly ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, nor with ſuch ordinances as be of earthie nature? For it is moſt manifeſt that all the trinkets and traſh of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27731:17"/> Maſſemongers, wherewithal they do iuggle &amp; play with their Mammets are earthly and tranſitorie: ſo is alſo their Temple and Altars, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently their prieſthood. And further alſo it is certaine that the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> might rather be called heauenly than theirs, becauſe it was the paterne of the heauenly, and he was called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that honour of God, but they can ſhewe no calling thereto at all. Who then is ſo blind but may ſée, that ſéeing the ſacrifice propitiatorie cannot be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred by an earthly Prieſt, nor with earthly ordinances, that the white cake which the vncleane ſhaueling the <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite</hi> doth holde vp ouer his head, is not the ſonne of God, but a dead Idol? If the blinde idolatous Papiſtes will obiect, that the efficacie of their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and prieſthood is heauenly, although it be executed on earth, they are to be aunſwered that if the efficacie of their prieſthood be heauenly, then is it eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but they are mortal and do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Prieſtes worlde without ende. Againe, the power of the ſacrifice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27731:18"/> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of the Prieſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo their ſacrifice is not eternall. This thing ſhalbe yet more manifeſt by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> further compariſon which is made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the ſacrifice of Chriſt, and thoſe of the lawe in the ſame <hi>Chapter, ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 13. &amp; 14. where it is ſhewed, that if the bloud of calues and of goates, and the aſhes of a red Heffer ſprinkling thoſe that were defiled, did ſanctifie as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the carnall purging: then howe much more ſhall the bloud of Chriſt, which by his eternall ſpirite, offred him ſelfe to God without ſpot, purge your conſcience from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God? This compariſon is brought in to prooue that Chriſt by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring once into the holie places, by his owne bloud, hath founde eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: for that being the ſumme of the two verſes going next before, is proued by this. It was graunted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controuerſie, that by reaſon of gods ordinance, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bloud of thoſe poore beaſts, and the water made with the aſhes of the Heffer, being but a dead thing, had power in ſome manner to purge, as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27731:18"/> namely that which he calleth the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal purging. For if a man were pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any outwarde pollution, and therefore might not come vnto thoſe holie thinges which were the carnall commandements, being but ſhadowes and ceremonies, yet if he were ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled with thoſe, although he were not purged within fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, he was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cleane: then how much more ſhall the bloud of the ſonne of God, which hath the power of life in it, becauſe it is the bloud of him that was not onely a man ſo holie that he was without ſpot, but alſo God? For herein lyeth the ſtrength of the argument which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ghoſt vſeth to prooue that Chriſt at once by his bloud hath purged the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from ſame for euer, that this ſacrifice was offred by his eternall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is his godhead. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godhed hauing eternall power of life, the fleſh and bloud of the man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od ioyned ſo with the godhead that they made one perſon, had alſo the ſame power, ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the bloud of Chriſt of it ſelfhad not power at once to purge eternally,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27731:19"/> yet becauſe it was the bloud of God, it had that force. Hereupon it followeth that the power of that purging by his bloud being eternall, and that one pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation being perfect, the redemption which he hath found is eternall. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we may ſtrongly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude againſt the Papiſtes, &amp; that with a double con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: Firſt, that ſéeing no ſacrifice hath the vertue to purge away ſinne, but becauſe it is offered by the eternall ſpirite, And ſecondly, that his purging once made, being that which is made by the eternall Godhead, is perfect for euer: By the firſt it is manifeſt that they are not able to offer a ſacrifice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatorie, becauſe they are mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the ſeconde, that there is no place for them, the worke of purging ſinne being alreadie accompliſhed for euer. If there be a newe redemption to be wrought, then let them be the prieſtes: in the meane time they are foule ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and ſacrilegious wretches, deſtroying the power of Chriſts death, when they will take vppon them to do that which he hath alreadie perfectly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27731:19"/> finiſhed. Come forth ye blind Papiſts, and proue that ye are more than men, ſhewe alſo that the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offered hath not an eternall and perfect power to purge away ſinne or elſe confeſſe that yours is Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Wee may ioyne hereunto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is vſed to proue that the ſacrifices of the <hi>Leuiticall</hi> Prieſtes did not purge ſinne: namely, that they were ſo often offered. For thereby the holie ghoſt doth teach that they were not able to ſanctifie the commers thereto, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 1. For then, as he ſayeth, they ſhoulde haue ceaſed, becauſe there ſhould haue béene no more conſcience of ſinne in the worſhippers, being once purged. The reaſon is manifeſt, drawen from the effect of the medicine: for if it haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the diſeaſe, and perfected the cure, then is it vaine to adde it any more. If it be ſtill continually, &amp; from time to time applyed to the ſore as ſtill remaining, then it may be ſaid truely, that the ſame medicine doeth not heale. Wherefore he addeth this proofe, that notwithſtanding the ſacrifices were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27731:20"/> yet there remained the mention of ſinnes yerely, when they kept that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rpiation. This diſeaſe of ſinne ſtill remaining, as the continuall mention &amp; remembrance there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. doeth ſhewe: it followeth, that thoſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did not nor could not purge it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Unto theſe is oppoſed the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, which becauſe it hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly purged ſinne for euer, ſo that there remaineth no more conſcience thereof in thoſe that are ſanctified: it is done but once, and neuer to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated or don again. The other which were Prieſtes in the lawe ſtoode daily miniſtring, and often offring the ſame ſacrifices, which coulde neuer take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſinne. But this man hauing offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one ſacrifice for ſinne, ſitteth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer at the right hand of God, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth waiting vntill his enimies be made his ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>loole, <hi>Heb. 10. ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11, 12.</hi> The former did ſtand daily mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ring as thoſe which had not, nor coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not accompliſh the work of reconcil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, although they offred neuer ſo often: But he hauing once offered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſeth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27731:20"/> from offring, and is ſet downe in the higheſt throne of maieſtie and glorie, becauſe as it is there ſaide, he hath with one oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made perfect for euer thoſe which are ſanctified. If his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice did aboliſh ſinne but for a time, as for a yere, or certaine yeres, then ſhould he either bring nothing to paſſe, or elſe returne often and ſundrie times from his glorie to offer againe. This is alſo confirmed in the ſame <hi>Chapter, ver.</hi> 18. by a concluſion which is drawen out of the forme of wordes which the Lorde vſeth in the promiſe which he maketh of the Newe Teſtament: as namely, that he will remember their ſinnes and their iniquities no more. He reaſoneth in this manner, where God remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not ſinne, there he hath giuen pardon and remiſſion, for that he col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teth, and where there is pardon, ther is no more ſacrifice for ſinne. Now therefore when we ſee this to be moſt manifeſt by the plaine doctrine of Gods worde, let vs conſider the abominable wickednes of the Papiſtes which by their ſacrifice ouerturne all this. For
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27731:21"/> whereas there is remiſſion of ſinnes alreadie purchaſed, what place can ther be for their ſacrifice propitiatorie? whereas that ſacrifice is vnperfect, and cannot take away ſinne which is often offred, how is theirs the perfect ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſtes bodie, which is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually done againe and againe? What do they leſſe therefore when they teach, that in the Maſſe they offer Chriſt to his father, to be a ſacrifice to take away ſinne: than affirme that the promiſe of the New Teſtament hath failed, &amp; that ſinne is yet remembred, no remi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion as yet obtained? And further, when they will needes haue him offred ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, is it not as much as to denye the effect and power of the bloud of Chriſt? Is it not quite contrarie to this, that with one oblation he hath made perfect for euer thoſe that are ſanctified? But here they take exception and ſay that they do not offer any new ſacrifice but the ſame: And moreouer that their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is but an application of the fruit of that which Chriſt offered, and that becauſe we ſée &amp; féele in our ſelues that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27731:21"/> we are ſtill guiltie: all which is but a blinde cauill. For what though they ſay they offer the ſame, did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> yerely offer ſtill the ſame? doth not the power of the reaſon ſtand in this, to proue that they were not auailable, becauſe then they ſhould haue ceaſed? Can they denie but that they offer often? Further, he doeth not place the perfect worke in the ſacrifice of Chriſt, becauſe it was but one, but becauſe it was but once offred: for he ſaith not with one ſacrifice, but with one offring hath he made perfect for euer thoſe which are ſanctified. This doth cut the throte of their ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offring, when his one offring had made perfect for euer: for it leaueth nothing behind for ſuch caitiues as they be. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where they pretende this neceſſitie becauſe we haue ſtill guiltie conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, therein they are more than beaſts: for the guiltineſſe of our conſciences is not for this, that there néedeth any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to be offered to ſatiſfie and purge ſinne: but through the remnants of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie which remaine in vs becauſe of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27731:22"/> the weaknes and imperfection of our faith, for in theſe we are not to looke to any ſatiſfaction yet behind, but to take hold of that perfect one which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie ſatiſfied. If that act of theirs bée propitiatorie, then is not ſinne fully diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>charged by the other. Thus blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous they are not onely in this their God of dough but alſo in all other their ſatiſfactions for ſinne, and in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Purgatorie. For if there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine any ſatiſfaction or purgation to be made, then is it not true that he hath made perfect for euer, neither was his death then of full and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent price. True it is, that although we are by his one oblation fully and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly diſcharged for euer before God, from the guiltines of our ſinnes: yet we are not in the full poſſeſſion of this benefite, nor ſhall not be vntill the laſt day, for then ſhall his enimies be made his footeſtoole. The diuell, ſinne &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th are theſe enimies which he hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, that they cannot raigne ouer vs: but yet wee muſt in the meane time wreſile with them, not therefore eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27731:22"/> the power of Chriſts death to be the leſſe, becauſe they be not alreadie vtterly aboliſhed, as the wicked vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuing Papiſtes do, and therefore ſet vp traſhe of their own to deſtroy ſinne, but waiting for that appointed time, when the full power of his death ſhall appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: in the meane time ſtaying by faith, &amp; reſting our ſelues on that one ſacrifice once offred. To conclude then, hath not the mightie ſpirite of God po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to apply vnto vs the vertue of that bloud: but ſuch ſillie vermin as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſts muſt help? The holy ghoſt calling vpon vs, and teaching vs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie theſe benefites, willeth vs to draw neere with a true heart, with full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith, <hi>Hebr. 10. ver.</hi> 22. we come vnto him with the heart, after a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall manner, becauſe all thinges in him are ſpiritual, we are did to approch to lay hold of him by faith, for wee can not either with the hande or with the mouth. And ſeeing there is not ſo much as one ſentence in all the booke of God, which ſpeaketh of any application of his death any other way, it muſt néedes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27731:23"/> be concluded againe that they may bée as good prieſtes as the prieſtes of <hi>Baal</hi> and no better, and that when they hold vp their idol, Chriſt is not betweene their fingers. Let vs go forward. It ſhal yet be more manifeſt by the words of the holie Ghoſt, that this ſacrifice of the Maſſe is ſo farre from being the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Newe Teſtament, that it doth flatly go againſt it. For he ſaith as concerning Chriſt, that he did not offer himſelfe often, as the high Prieſt went yerely into the holie place with other bloud, <hi>Hebr. 9. ver.</hi> 25. and then in the next verſe he giueth a reaſon, namely, that then he ſhould haue ſuffred often ſince the beginning of the world. This ſentence is verie mightie againſt the Papiſtes, becauſe it driueth them from all their ſhiftes, and leaueth them na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and deſtitute: but the force of it wil not appeare vnleſſe we looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what principles it is grounded, to proue that if Chriſt ſhould haue offered himſelfe often, then muſt he alſo haue ſuffered death often ſince the beginning of the world. Among the which this offreth it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27731:23"/> ſelfe as the firſt to be conſidered, that all the holie fathers, the Patriarches and Prophets from the beginning, coulde haue no entrance vnto God but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and that whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they had the dore ſhut againſt them, by this they were reſtored into fauour, and receiued. For it cannot be denyed, but that by nature they were ſinners as we be: and that God cannot receiue ſinners. Being therefore out of controuerſie that they obteined life, it muſt néedes followe that they had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: for if either there had béene no ſin, or no pardon to be graunted, what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie could there be of a ſacrifice? The ſeconde principle without which the reaſon of the Apoſtle cannot ſtande is this, that there can be no remiſſion but onely by the ſacrifice of Chriſt: for if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſacrifice, or any other way or meane might obtaine it, then were ther not a neceſſitie, why he ſhoulde often ſuffer. For although ther were a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of remiſſion of ſinnes, vnleſſe all ſhould be damned, yet he might be ſet free from the ſame neceſſitie of offring
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27731:24"/> himſelfe, ſéeing there were other wayes to obtaine it, but the holie Ghoſt ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vppon this as a marter not to bee doubted of, that neither there is, nor neuer hath béene any thing able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſinne, or to take away the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it by making ſatiſfaction, but onely the ſacrifice of the ſonne of God. For howſoeuer the idolatrous Innvels do aſcribe vnto many things they power of purging, and ſatiſfying for ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yet the holie word of God, and thoſe which beléeue it do giue that glorie only vnto Chriſt, and euen as his great glorie, wherein he hathne fellow. The third thing without which, an exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ption might be iuſtly taken againſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reaſon is this, that there co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be no oblation of Chriſt, but he muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death: for when he ſayeth he ſhould not offer him ſelfe often. he addeth this cauſe, that then he ſhould haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed often. It were an eaſie matter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the offring of Chriſt were any thing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable without ſuffring death, to ſay there were no neceſſitie wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee ſhould ſuffer often, ſeeing he might bee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27731:24"/> offred, and not be ſlaine. But this is ſtrengthened by that which goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> where hee hath ſhewed that the teſtament is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed when men are dead, becauſe it is of no force while the teſtator liueth, and ſo he is the mediator of the Newe Teſtament, but yet through death. Wherefore alſo the former teſtament, in which there were but the ſhadowes and paterne of heauenly thinges, was ratified by death, as it is prooued by this, that it was not dedicated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloud. For when <hi>Moſes</hi> had read the lawe vnto the people, he tooke the bloud of calues and Goates, with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and purple Woll and Hyſſop, he ſprinkled both the booke and the people, ſaying, this is the blould of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which god hath commaunded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Likewiſe alſo he ſprinkled the Tabernacle and all the miniſtring veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels with bloud, and almoſt all things, ſayeth he, by the law are purged with bloud, and without ſhedding of bloud, there is no remiſſion. Here is then a manifeſt reaſon wherfore Chriſt could
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27731:25"/> not be offred often, but he muſt then alſo dye often: euen becauſe the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of no force without the death of the teſtator. Here is further ſhewed wherefore it cannot be auailable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death, that is to ſay, there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes without ſhedding of bloud. Chriſt therefore could not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſſe it ſhould be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which is moſt abſurde, but his bloud muſt be often ſhed. Then if the Papiſtes will vpholde and maintaine that their ſacrifice is auailable to purge away ſinne, and that it is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice propitiatorie for the quicke &amp; the dead, as they doe impudently affirme: Let them alſo confeſſe that they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe the ſonne of God, and ſo ſhead his bloud. For if they will ſtande to this, that theirs is an vnbloudie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and though they offer him, yet they do not ſlay him, and yet withall do challenge the power therby to purge ſinne: let them knowe that they goe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the ſpirite of God which ſayeth there is no remiſſion without ſhedding of bloud. In this therefore
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27731:25"/> they are after an horrible manner blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, that they will ouerthrowe the reaſon and argument of the holie ghoſt. For if by any means there might be a ſacrifice to take away ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſhedding of bloud, then might Chriſt haue béen often offred and haue dyed but once. If the fathers had the fruite and benefite of that one oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as namely their ſinnes waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with that bloud once ſhed, &amp; that without any offring of ſuch vnbloudie ſacrifice to apply the ſame: why ſhould not wee likewiſe by faith obtaine the ſame, vnleſſe ſome ſhaueling offer him daily? Ye blinde Idolaters, did y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bloud of Chriſt purge away ſinne before his comming, onely through faith, and ſhal it not now? Was there a more perfect power in it to aboliſh ſinne, in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which were long time before his comming, than there is after it hath béene ſhed in déede? For if it be ſo that the fathers had their ſinnes waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with Chriſtes bloud, and yet no offring of him to apply the ſame, but apprchended through faith, ſhall it not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27731:26"/> deſtroy the vertue therof, or at the leaſt diminiſh it, when they teach that wee cannot be partakers of him, vnleſſe he be ſtill offred? Is that which the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh, that he hath béene once made manifeſt in the ende of the world, to aboliſh ſinne, by the offring himſelfe to be referred onely to the fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming? Doth not the reaſon following extend it vnto vs as wel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea euen vnto the whole Church, vntill his comming againe at the worldes ende? for he compareth it in this maner: that as it is appointed vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dye once, and after commeth iudgement: ſo Chriſt alſo being once offred to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of manie, vnto thoſe that looke for him ſhall appeare the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time without ſinne, vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is the ordinance of God that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man hath runne his race and finiſhed his courſe, he ſhall not be permitted to turne backe againe to do that which he left vndone, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make ſtraight that which is crooked, but muſt holde him vnto iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for things paſt, becauſe that onely remameth. In like ſort he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27731:26"/> ſetteth the perfection of the one oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, who being once offered to take away the ſinnes of manie, it is ſo perfectly doone, that when he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare againe the ſeconde time to giue the eternall ſaluation, there ſhalbe no ſinne to be purged, or for which he is to make further ſatiſfaction. For when it is ſaide, that he ſhall appeare without ſinne the ſecond time, it is not meant of his owne perſon, but of thoſe whome he hath redéemed from their ſinnes: which is moſt cléere and manifeſt in this, that the minde of the holie Ghoſt, is to ſhewe a difference betwéene his firſt and ſeconde appearance, euen in that point. Which if it ſhould be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of his owne perſon ſhould make no difference, becauſe he was without ſinne at his firſt appearing, although he tooke vpon him, and bare in his bodie the ſinnes of his people: But at his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde appearance becauſe he hath vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed ſinne for euer, there ſhal be none to be borne of him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none for which he ſhall againe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice. The Papiſts, but that they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27731:27"/> be impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, might be aſhamed to patch in their trumperie, to giue power vnto the death of Chriſt, when they ſée here the perfection of it ſo ſet foorth, that it hath ſo at once for euer deſtroyed ſinne, that there néedeth no more ſacrifice to be offred. For will they make the power of it leſſe ſince his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming than it was before? We may then conclude, ſéeing the ſacrifice of the Newe Teſtament, that ſhould haue a ſpirituall, heauenly, and endleſſe power could not be offred in a worldly ſanctuarie, with worldly ordinances: the ſanctuarie and all the ordinances of the Popiſh ſeruice and Prieſthood are ſuch, as are earthly, and ſéeing the ſame ſacrifice coulde not be offred to be auailable, vnleſſe it were offred by the eternall godhead, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſtes are men and not God: &amp; being the bloud of a man which is alſo God, that purgeth away ſinne, it hath an eternall power to purge: and ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Papiſtes will haue a newe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, there is no place for their propitiatorie ſacrifice, And ſéeing the ſacrifice that is perfect is but once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27731:27"/> that which is often offred doeth not take away ſinne. And becauſe the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offred hath for euer perfectly aboliſhed ſinne, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Newe Teſtament is that God will no more remember it: and therefore no more ſacrifice to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The Papiſtes contrarie to that promiſe make ſatiſfactions ſtill and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for ſinne. Their ſacrifice is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred often. Chriſt coulde be offred but once, becauſe he could by but once. The ſacrifice is not auailable without death becauſe there is no remiſſion of ſinnes, without ſhedding of bloud. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes do not ſaye they ſlay Chriſt, they ſay theirs is an vnblodie ſacrifice: there is no remiſſion of ſinnes without ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud. The ſacrifice of Poperie is not the ſacrifice of the Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither can it be propitiatorie, as they bragge, for the quick &amp; the dead. Nay it is as abominable before God, as if a man ſhould offer a dogge in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Then conſidering what iniury theſe Prieſts after the order of Rome, haue done vnto the ſonne of God, firſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27731:28"/> in challenging that office and dignitie, which belongeth onely vnto him: and ſecondly in ouer throwing the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vertue and efficacie of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Let as many of vs, as minde to cleaue vnto Chriſt, to take part with him, and to fight vnder his banner, &amp; ſo attaine the reward of eternal glory, remoue our ſelues vtterly from the campe and ſocietie of ſuch aduerſaries: and armed with the ſpirituall armour of God, let vs ſounde the trumpet, and bid defiance againſt them, and againſt the diuel, and Antichriſt their chiefe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaines, for this is moſt certaine, that wee ſhall neuer be reputed as friendes vnto Chriſt, vnleſſe wee be at enm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty with his enimies, &amp; fight againſt them. Manie do ſuppoſe that they may hold friendſhip and familiaritie with them, and eſtéeme of them as Chriſtians, and match their ſonnes with their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, although they beare y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame print, and be of the ſame ſtamp with their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: onely becauſe they doe profeſſe the name of Chriſt, and carrie a zeale vnto him. But this dooth bewray a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27731:28"/> moſt horrible blindnes, &amp; groſſe darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, which cannot ſée, that to confeſſe the name of Chriſt is not anie thing at all auailable, ſéeing they doe vnder that pretence rob and ſpoyle him of his glorie, &amp; tread downe his trueth, and deſtroy his lawes. The Apoſtle ſayeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. that the Iewes had the zeale of God, but yet he ſayeth it was not according to knowledge, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that being not a ſpirituall, but a carnall zeale, could nothing at al cléere them, but that they were ſtill thoſe which as vtter enimies of god did fight againſt him. In like ſort although it be graunted that the Papiſtes haue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion towards Chriſt, yet what doth it helpe them, ſéeing it is a carnall and blind deaotion? our ſauiour Chriſt ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. that the Scribes &amp; Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſées did build the tombes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and garniſh the ſepulchres of the righteous, and ſaide, that if they had béene in the dayes of their fathers, they would not haue béene partakers with them in the bloud of the Prophets: but yet for all this their forwardneſſe and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27731:29"/> good will to honour the Prophets, and to diſalowe of their fathers in killing them, he threateneth them, that all the righteous bloud ſhead vppon the earth, ſhould come vpon them, and why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would ſend Prophets, &amp; leſſe men and Scribes vnto them: and of them they ſhoulde kill and crucifie: and of them they ſhould ſcourge in their ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogs, and perſecute from citie to ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. They were then guiltie, and had their part in the bloud of the former Prophets, becauſe they murthered thoſe of their time. Euen ſo is this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bloudie generation of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes: they haue ſuch a zeale to the Saints of God that were of olde, that they would honour them with diuine worſhip, when as in the meane time they perſecute and murther all thoſe which imbrace and follow the doctrine of thoſe holy ones. Shall not they the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be guiltie of all the bloud of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs whome they ſéeme to loue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as the Scribes and Phariſees did the Prophets, when as by all kinde of cruell trecheries, by treaſons &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27731:29"/> they ſéeke to murther, &amp; deſtroy all thoſe which beare any loue to the glorious Goſpell of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and that will not fall downe &amp; worſhip y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beaſt nor receiue his mark? If euer there were helhoundes that could not be ſatiſfied with bloud, theſe are they which woulde ſpare neither high nor lowe, Prince nor ſubiect, yong nor olde. If euer there were damnable heretikes, and abominable idolaters vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, theſe are they, which ground all their worſhip vppon the deuiſes of men, reiecting the holie ſcriptures, and taking the honour due vnto God &amp; his ſonne Chriſt, and giuing it vnto crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, worſhipping for God a cake made of flower. Is it not then ful time that we giue eare to the voice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</hi> 18. 4. Is it not plainly ſaide by the Angel, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14. 9. that if any man worſhip the beaſt, and his image, &amp; ſhall receiue the marke in his forehead, or in his hande: he ſhall alſo drinke of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27731:30"/> wine of the wrath of God, euen of the vndelayed wine, which is powred forth into the cup of his wrath, and he ſhalbe tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holie Angels, and in the preſence of the Lambe, &amp; the ſmoke of their torment ſhall aſcende worlde without end: and they ſhal haue no reſt day nor night which worſhip the beaſt and his image, and if any receiue the print of his name. Being as cléere as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Sunne at noone dayes vnto all thoſe which haue eyes to ſée, that Rome is that Babylon, and the Pope that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage and cruell beaſt, ought it not to driue vs as far from them as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, to renounce their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and falſe idolatrous worſhip, to pack vp all their traſh, and ſend it home to Rome, to aboliſh their lawes, to flye their fellowſhip &amp; ſocietie, to be at vtter enmitie with them in this reſpect that they be the ſworne enimies of Chriſt? What honour is there left vnto the ſonne of God, when ſuch vile caiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es ſhall take vppon them to be partakers with him in the office and dignitie of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27731:30"/> the mediatorſhip? For when as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and enmitie betwéene God &amp; men was ſuch, that there coulde be no agréement nor vnitie, becauſe God is moſt perfectly holie and pure, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but hate that which is foule, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto his nature: there was none to approch vnto him to be the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwéene him and them, which was in ſo high fauour as that they might be accepted through him, nor of ſuch power as to be able to aunſwere, &amp; diſcharge whatſoeuer they coulde bee charged withall: but ſuch an one as was alſo moſt holie and pure. While the Tabernacle did ſtande, and the moſt holie place which did repreſent heauen, the high Prieſt was the mediatour: for when the people were ſhut foorth, hee went in before the Arke to offer &amp; make prayer for them. But thoſe thinges were but ſhadowes, and his conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was carnall. He was a poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, not able to purchaſe fauour for himſelfe. He was a Prieſt agréea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that couenant, but no wretched ſinner can be the mediator of the newe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27731:31"/> couenant, to ſtande betwéene God and the people, that he may obtaine fauour and remiſſion of ſinnes for them, but he which is vnſpotted. Alas what caſe then are thoſe men in, which take a poore Popiſh Prieſt, which is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſooine in lecherie, to be their Prieſt to ſtande betweene God &amp; them, to offer for them, that by him they may haue their ſinnes pardoned? Doth not <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay, the wicked cannot ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? How then ſhall any of them ſtande as a Prieſt before him to be a mediator? Doth not the holy Ghoſt ſay by <hi>Salomon,</hi> that the ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is an abomination to the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an that which the Lord doth eſteeme as a thing abominable, be a ſacrifice propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatorie? Can that which God doeth curſſe and hate, clenſe away ſinne? The Lord in mercie open the eyes of poore ſimple men which haue beene ſeduced &amp; miſled, that they may ſee what a deceipt this is, that a man ſhalbe made to ſeek life in that which is one of the greateſt ſinnes that can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet a poore rotten worme in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27731:31"/> place and office of Chriſt, a vile fil thie ſinner is to come before God with a ſacrifice. Nowe as they he idolatrous prieſtes, by their cake which they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as God, ouerthrowing as much as lyeth in their power, the ſacrifice of Chriſt, and fighting vnder the banner of the diuel againſt God, ſo alſo their fruites do follow accordingly, &amp; declare what manner of trees they be. Do they not maintaine lying and periurie, all kinde of diſſembling, and falſe treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to obtaine their purpoſes, and to bring their miſchieuous and diueliſh practiſes to effect? Are they not bloudy murtherers and traitors againſt their lawfull ſoueraigne Prince? Let them ſhewe where euer <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> or anie Apoſtle of Chriſt hath taught the like, or put it in practiſe. If not, then let vs conclude againſt them, that they be of their father the diuel, who is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all falſhod, and a murtherer, the worker of all treaſons againſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And let all men which haue any care to ſaue their ſoules be ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liking of them, or conſenting to them,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27731:32"/> that they can ſay with the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, do not I hate them that hate thée, O Lord, am I not irkeſomely g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eued with thoſe that riſe vp againſt thee? I hate them with a perfect hatred, I take them as enimies to my ſelfe. This zeale ought to be for the glorie of Chriſt in all true Chriſtians, this loue ſetled in the hearts of all faithfull ſubiects to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their Prince. There is no te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of any goodnes in men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this: for thoſe men which can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo willingly euen in their boſoms theſe vipers, as ſome do their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues, their ſonnes, their daughters, their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and their friends: although they make ſome ſhewe, as though they did ſome what miſlike, yet they be verie Atheiſts, voide of all true knowledge, and feare of God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27731:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
